<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>machine learning | Philip Ekfeldt</title>
    <link>/category/machine-learning/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>machine learning</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:40:59 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>machine learning</title>
      <link>/category/machine-learning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bird&#39;s Eye View Layout Prediction</title>
      <link>/project/dl_project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 00:40:59 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dl_project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this project we focus on Bird&amp;rsquo;s Eye View (BEV) prediction based on monocular photos taken by the cameras on top of the car. We present a Maximum Mean Discrepancy Variational Auto Encoder (MMD VAE) model to predict the BEV road layout. We also contribute an approach combining Image Warping, U-Net and Post-processing to predict the bounding boxes (BB) on the BEV layout. Our models achieve &lt;strong&gt;0.81 test threat score on the road layout prediction task and 0.072 test threat score on the BB prediction task&lt;/strong&gt;. Animations below visualize the predictions of our final models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter and Stellar Stream Detection</title>
      <link>/project/capstone_2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 23:14:10 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/capstone_2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stellar stream and dark matter detection are active areas of research in astrophysics. Historically, this detection has been a manual process and has led to the discovery
of stellar streams such as GD-1 and Palomar 5. If astrophysicists initially have strong confidence that certain stars are part of a stellar stream, probabilistic methods
may determine the likelihood that an adjacent star also belongs to the same stellar stream. Using machine learning methods, we seek to develop an automated process
that finds additional stars that are part of the stellar stream. After initially trying standardized classification methods, we establish an ensemble of a subset of kNN
methods (ESkNN) as an effective means of classifying stars from simulated streams and real streams. Since these methods generally fail to capture non-linearities in the
data, we also use a feedforward neural network approach that we expected to help capture non-linear properties. Our evaluation metric for these two metrics is the F1
score. The best model produced by ESkNN method had an F1 score of 0.75, when evaluated on GD-1 stars. The deep learning method (DeepSets) achieved an F1
score of 0.66. While both approaches can be tuned to prefer precision or recall, the ESkNN tends towards highly precise results (99%) whereas the DeepSets method
tends towards results with high recall. We also attempt a metric learning approach that could help uncover a distance learning metric that is an improvement upon Euclidean distance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
